Hello everyone and welcome to
English Pod, my name is Marco.
My name is Catherine
and today we have a very
very useful intermediate level
lesson for you all about the weather.
That's right so obviously we have seen the
news and sometimes on the news we have the
weather report so today
we're going to learn
all about that weather
report in English.
So let's check out today's dialogue and
we'll be back in a moment to talk about the
words and phrases that
those weather forecasters used.
And those are today's top stories.
Now let's go to John for the weather.
John what does the forecast
look like for our weekend travelers?
I'm afraid we're in for
a rough weekend Mary.
There's a storm system
moving through the east coast.
It will be drizzling all
day today and there's
a sixty percent chance of
thunderstorms this evening.
It will be warm and humid
all weekend in the Midwest
expects strong winds and a
low over around forty degrees.
That's pretty chilly for the summer.
Will it rain on Saturday?
Unfortunately yes.
It will be clearly Saturday
morning but there
is a high chance of showers and
thunderstorms later in the day.
There is a severe thunderstorm
warning for some parts of the southeast.
In those areas might see
some hail and flooding
especially in areas that have been
experiencing record high rainfalls.
That certainly sounds like a jury Saturday.
It gets better on Sunday though.
The storm systems move east
and the skies will clear up at night.
It will still be rather cool
at highs in the low fifties.
The west coast will
be experiencing some
unusually chilly weather but
at least the sun will come out.
I advise weekend travelers to be careful
especially while driving back to you Mary.
Thanks John and there you have it.
Looks like it's a weekend to stay at home.
Alright we're back so
apparently they're not
going to have great
weather this weekend and
they actually started
with an interesting
word and actually the
commentator started with
asking the weather man John what does
the forecast look like for our weekend?
Ok so the word here
forecast is very very
important because it describes
this part of the newscast.
A forecast is basically
a prediction or a
description of the
future weather situation.
That's right so we're talking
about the weather forecast.
Now it's very interesting
because we can also
use that in business
for example in budgets
you can say what is the
financial forecast of the company.
Alright so you can't
know what will happen but
you can predict it and
that's what a forecast is.
That's right.
So we're talking about the weather forecast
and the weather man said that well there
are some storms coming
and it will be drizzling all day.
Ok so to drizzle is a verb
and it's like the verb to
rain except it's less by
degree so it's very light rain.
Yeah it's kind of
like if I spray you with
water, not a spray can or
something it's like drizzle.
Little dots of water it's
not like you're getting wet.
You don't really have the
normal heavy raindrops
you just have a little bit
of water coming down.
But it's annoying
because do you bring your
umbrella do you believe
your umbrella so drizzling
is a kind of rain
that's very very light.
That's right.
Alright so it's going
to drizzle all day and
the weather man also said that
we might have some thunderstorms.
Ok so thunderstorms are very different.
Waterstorms are a kind
of storm where there
is thunder so thunder is the
loud noises when there's lightning.
Oh lightning.
Ok so lightning is like the flash that you
get from the sky and thunder is the hard
sound that comes after
the boom that's right.
So remember it light lightning.
Light is the light that comes
down from the sky lightning and
thunderstorms are just those
loud noises that the lightning makes.
So usually with thunderstorms
we have very heavy rain.
That's right and that's why it's different
from drizzling which is very light.
Ok now we're talking about water
we have drizzle we have thunderstorm.
Now what about a shower because the weather
man said there is a high chance of showers.
Well yes there's a high chance of showers I
take showers every day thank you very much
but that's not the kind of shower
we're talking about here is it.
That's right.
Think about it though it's similar.
A shower when you wash yourself
is water coming down on top of you.
Well in this case it's a rain
shower so it's rain that's happening.
Ok so it's rain water
that's coming down very
similar to the shower that
you take in the morning.
The difference though is that a shower is a
noun and to rain is a verb so it will rain
tomorrow or we expect showers
tomorrow both mean the same thing.
Alright very good
and well talking about
showers and thunderstorms
there's also another
type of water that falls
from the sky this is called hail.
Ok so hail is difficult to describe because
it's like ice but it's not really it's just
usually hard almost
like marbles like hard
balls of rain that come
down so it's not snow.
That's right.
It hurts when it hits you.
Sometimes it's very big
sometimes it's very small but
it's heavy hard things
that come out of the clouds.
So just think about
it it's very very similar
to ice it's the small
pieces of ice coming
down from the from
the sky so that's hail but
obviously very different from snow because
as we said it's hard snow is very soft.
And well with this type
of weather going on
in the weekend the commentator said wow that
certainly sounds like a dreary saturday.
Ok dreary is a great word to describe it
so as you can tell it's going to rain it's
dreary is not a good
thing it's not a happy thing.
Ok so something is dreary when it's not
very exciting it looks like it'll be dull or
sad or boring or dark.
Now can you describe
a person like this as well?
Yes he's a very dreary
person he's never
optimistic he's always down and yeah
kind of quiet and sad and down boring.
Ok so that's what it means something that's
boring not very exciting or very calm but
also dark there's a dark
element to it because
he's dreary you know
there's no sunshine
there's no light there's no optimism
so you can say it's a dreary day.
Yeah very dreary day
today no light no sunshine.
Ok very good we've taken a look at a lot of
vocab there when we review what we've just
learned and listened to the dialogue again.
And those are today's top stories
now let's go to John for the weather.
John what does the forecast
look like for our weekend travelers?
I'm afraid we're in for a rough weekend
Mary there's a storm system moving through
the east coast it will
be drizzling all day
today and there's a 60%
chance of thunderstorms
this evening it will be warm
and humid all weekend in the
Midwest expects strong winds
and a low over around 40 degrees.
That's pretty chilly for the
summer will it rain on Saturday.
Unfortunately yes it
will be clearly Saturday
morning but there is a high chance of
showers and thunderstorms later in the day.
There is a severe thunderstorm
warning for some parts of the southeast.
Folks in those areas
might see some hail and
flooding especially in
areas that have been
experiencing record high rainfalls.
That certainly sounds like a jury Saturday.
It gets better on Sunday
though the storm systems
movies to the skies
will clear up at night.
It will still be rather cool
with highs in the low 50s.
The west coast will
be experiencing some
unusually chilly weather but
at least the sun will come out.
I advise weekend travelers to be careful
especially while driving back to you Mary.
Thanks John and there you have it.
Looks like it's a weekend to stay at home.
Alright we're back so
now we're going to talk
a little bit about some phrases that we've
chosen for you on Floying Sea Builder.
Fluency Builder.
So when we're talking
about forecasts remember
that we're talking about
things that aren't certain.
We have to explain
that there is a possibility
of rain or a possibility of sunshine and
usually in the weather report they will use
percentages to describe how
likely something is to happen.
That's right the weatherman said
there is a 60% chance of thunderstorms.
Okay so 60% is not very
likely but it's also not unlikely.
It means that it might
happen that it rains.
That's right so as you said it's a way to
measure what the probabilities are because
imagine if the weatherman
says it might rain
tomorrow you're like
well maybe it really
will or maybe it's very unlikely
that it won't or we don't really know.
Exactly so for example if the weatherman
says there's a 95% chance of rain tomorrow.
Do you bring your umbrella?
Yes.
It says there's a 5% chance
of rain tomorrow now no.
So you have to think about the probability.
60% it's maybe half and half
but 95% it's very likely to happen.
That's right and you also
mentioned there's a high chance of
thunderstorms or maybe you
can say there's a low chance of hail.
Right so he's basically saying he or she
is basically saying you know it's possible
that this will happen
or it's it's not likely
that this will happen they're
just they're trying to help you out.
They can't say this will happen
because they don't know.
Okay so the word for
probability here the
keyword is chance there is a good chance
that it will rain so chance is probability.
Right so for example
what's the chance it
will rain tomorrow well
there's a high chance.
Okay very good okay
and now when we talk
about the degrees or
the how warm or cold it is.
So we express it in
Fahrenheit in some
countries or in other
countries in centigrade.
Here we talk about
40 degrees Fahrenheit
but the weatherman
also says highs and lows.
There's a a low of around 40
degrees what does he mean a low?
This is a really
important part of the
forecast because you
need to know will you have
to bring a coat tomorrow
is it going to be hot
or cold and so you
think about a day usually
during the day at noon
or one o'clock in the
afternoon it's the
hottest but at night it's
the coldest and so
the low refers to the
lowest temperature and
the highest temperature.
So for example in the
fall maybe the highs are 60
degrees but the lows are
40 so you should bring a coat.
Okay means at night it'll be
40 during the day it'll be 60.
Okay so we're talking
about the highs or the
highest temperatures or the highest number
that we'll get and the lows is the lowest
so the weatherman will
commonly say tomorrow
will experience a high of
32 degrees and a low of 25.
So it's very easy to
understand that the
temperature during the day
will be between these two now.
Right.
Very good.
Okay and for our last
phrase the weatherman
also said that there is
a severe thunderstorm
warning for some
parts of the southeast.
All right so Marco this
is a really key phrase
because it's telling
people about potential
danger you know a thunderstorm can be
very dangerous so you want to stay inside.
So a severe thunderstorm
warning severe means
very very serious is something
you should pay attention to.
That's right but now the interesting thing
is that we can change the noun in this case
thunderstorm and we can talk about
for example a severe tornado warning.
All right so if there's
a severe tornado
warning then I really
have to pay attention to
the weather and be careful not to go outside
or even a severe flood warning you need
to know that the streets might
become flooded and prepare.
So they're saying
that there's a very high
probability that this might happen so
they're warning you to take precaution.
All right so pay
attention to that last one
and we're going to
listen to today's dialogue
one more time we'll be back in a moment to
talk a little bit more about the weather.
And those are today's top stories.
Now let's go to John for the weather.
John what does the forecast
look like for our weekend travelers?
I'm afraid we're in for
a rough weekend Mary.
There's a storm system
moving through the east coast.
It will be drizzling all
day today and there's
a 60% chance of
thunderstorms this evening.
It will be warm and humid
all weekend in the Midwest
expects strong winds and
a low of around 40 degrees.
That's pretty chilly for the summer.
Will it rain on Saturday?
Unfortunately yes.
It will be clearly Saturday
morning but there
is a high chance of showers and
thunderstorms later in the day.
There is a severe thunderstorm
warning for some parts of the southeast.
Folks in those areas
might see some hail and
flooding especially in
areas that have been
experiencing record high rainfalls.
That certainly sounds like a jury Saturday.
It gets better on Sunday though.
The storm systems move east
and the skies will clear up at night.
It will still be rather cool
with highs in the low fifties.
The west coast will
be experiencing some
unusually chilly weather but
at least the sun will come out.
I advise weekend travelers to be careful
especially while driving back to you Mary.
Thanks John and there you have it.
Looks like it's a weekend to stay at home.
All right so talking about
the weather it always
seems like the
weatherman is always wrong.
Always it's like it's like the
opposite of what should happen.
That's right.
But you know you can't
blame them because
all they have is a
computer and some sensors
and they have to guess about the weather
and help people figure out what to do.
Have you ever experienced
anything severe like
a like a heart thunderstorm or
maybe a tornado or something like this?
I have actually because
I'm from Chicago and
in America the middle
of the country is called
the tornado belt that means it's a piece
of land where tornadoes are very common.
And so in the fall and
in the spring we often
have tornadoes and I've been
in a couple tornadoes myself.
All right.
Have you seen them?
Yes.
There is an amazing to see.
They're very scary.
You're always running inside and
locking yourself in the basement.
It's very important
to protect yourself in
a tornado because it's
very dangerous around
the area of the tornado
because the wind is
so strong that trucks
and cars and telephone
poles and big, big, heavy objects
can fly through the air and hurt people.
And that's how most of the damage happens.
Okay.
So this is interesting because a tornado
is also considering natural disaster.
Yes it is.
But it's a weather phenomenon
whereas earthquakes
are a natural disaster but
it's not part of the weather.
Now yeah, you're right.
It's not something that
sweeps in and it leaves
like a flood for
example, all of the rain
will come down and it
will create a flood and
earthquake is a natural disaster
that's not weather related.
That's right.
Okay.
Interesting things though.
Maybe some of our
listeners that live in a very
cold area have experienced
a heavy snowstorm.
Like a blizzard or maybe people in a
tropical area have experienced a hurricane.
So let us know if you've ever been in
one of these weather related phenomenons.
And also if you have any comments or
questions, we're always at EnglishPod.com.
We hope to see you guys there.
All right.
Bye.